So one way to make sense of the problems you encounter
is to think about the problem-solving time horizon.
And I often think about it in three ways.
There's problem solving in the moment. There's problem solving where
you may have a week or two weeks to come to an answer.
And there's problem solving over a longer-term project.
In each of those cases, there are different aspects
of the problem-solving process that you might want to focus on.
So when you're problem solving in the moment, it's really critical to think about:
have you defined the problem and thought about all the constraints in the solution set?
You might not have time to formally whip out a sheet of paper
and go through each of the approaches and tools. But the question is:
what thinking can you do to really test, in that moment,
have you really defined the problem?
Have you aligned all the stakeholders on that? And have you thought about
whether the solution space we're looking at is well scoped?
When you're problem solving in one to two weeks, you've got a little more time
to do that analysis — but not a lot of time.
There can be more things you probably want to look at
than you have time to do.
And really, in that one-to-two-week time horizon, it's thinking about
how you prioritize the issues and analyses you want to conduct.
When you're thinking about problem solving in terms of a longer-term project,
you've got more time. But in those cases you probably also have more complexity.
There's probably a lot of value at stake. And in those cases,
you want to think about what is the right way to work-plan,
and think about: what are the dependencies?
What are the stakeholders you need to align?
What decisions do you need to come to early in the process
that may have knock-on effects later in the project's lifespan?